yeah don't you hate that advertis that
advertising is so lame it's like read
this one book and it's like an NBA it's
like no no cuz you you have to read at
least like eight books to get an MBA
like there's no way you can get NBA at
of one book but you can get an MBA like
education by joining the business Buyers
Club listening to acquisitive and
visiting the deal
Academy yeah take the deal Academy
courses be in the business Buyers Club
listen to acquisitive and you know
you're better than an NBA I don't have
an NBA so I can't really specifically PR
well cuz we don't need one because we do
all exactly look at
[Music]
us reading and dodging all the quick
sches money like your Spotify boy I got
T streams be real big I got make it just
for my kids for kids hi I'm Daniel and
I'm Sarah and this is acquisitive where
we break down Veil acquisition position
deals to make sure that you make it all
the way to the closing table this is
episode three and our guest today is
Brian zap Brian is a fractional CFO who
helps Law Firm owners with their
finances to make sure that they run a
machine not a job and can improve their
cash flow and uh Brian I'll let you tell
us a little bit more about your
background what you do today and what
you come or where you come from in the
world of m&a
thanks Daniel thanks Sarah it's great to
be here on the show um yeah so like
Daniel said I'm the founder of a
fractional CFO firm we work specifically
for marketing purposes we're working
with lawyers that's that's our Niche but
really we can help you know all types of
service business owners um I've got a
pretty broad background in you know
Finance and Accounting I've got my CPA
got an NBA in Finance and Accounting and
I've spent the past 15 plus years
working in all areas of Finance and
Accounting trying to put together the
tools that I can ultimately bring to
small businesses to help them make sure
that they're maximizing their returns
from their business or from their
investment um so I've got a lot of m&a
experience working with businesses
ranging from a million in sales up to 20
million in sales um I've got Hands-On
due diligence experience trying to make
sure you know kind of like if you go and
buy a car that you've got the carfax
report and that you're kicking the tire
so you know that you're not buying a
lemon and we can talk about that later
in the show if that's helpful um so a
lot of due diligence experience a lot of
Hands-On operational accounting
experience I've worked with Fortune 100
companies uh with some of their startup
businesses helping them improve
operations and then use their financials
to grow their business and then I've
also got experience just with financial
growth Consulting for midsize companies
so you know what's the story that our
numbers are telling are there
opportunities to improve our results and
how do we ensure ultimately when we're
ready to sell the business or if we're
looking to buy a business that we've got
everything in place for that so I know
I'm throwing a lot at you happy to
answer any questions that's really great
I you know before we dive in I've been
asking this question uh anybody that I
can find so we know that we know from
the news that CEOs of midsize businesses
200 million plus are are constantly
buying other businesses so C CEOs of
these uh large or mediumsized companies
technically are buying other businesses
that's just it's a known thing when
should a CEO go from working in the
business to on it and then from more
importantly from on it to acquiring and
acquiring their growth buying
competitors or adjacent Services that's
a great question and obviously you know
when you first start a business a lot of
times you'll start a business because
you have a specific skill right lawyers
start law firms uh you know HVAC
repairmen start hbac repair businesses
so early on before you've got a lot of
customers it really is you doing
everything for the business but as you
start to get your feet wet you really
understand that there's a lot to running
a business that is goes beyond just the
skill that you're really good at and
it's a lot of skill sets you know like
like the financial op operations the
sales and marketing um even just the
administrative operations that maybe you
didn't think through and that maybe you
know the founder or the business owner
really isn't equipped to handle so once
you've got kind of that initial set of
customers under your belt um you're
starting to get traction you know you've
probably hit low six figures in Revenue
that's a great time to start maybe
Outsourcing some of that help um and and
I would say first probably your first
hire really does need to be a virtual
assistant someone who's almost like a
second brain for you right and kind of
can take a lot of the administrative
tasks off your plate um in terms of
someone like myself you know like a
fractional CFO that really doesn't make
sense for most businesses until they get
up to a million or so in Revenue um but
once they hit that inflection point they
realize that what got them to that point
isn't going to get them to the next
stage so it helps to bring in you a
fractional CFO who's you know like like
it's in the name it's a fraction of the
cost of a full-time CFO who can be 200
300K a year in salary plus benefits you
can get someone for a fraction of the
price who can make sure your numbers are
helping you get to that next level and
then in terms of m&a like it's it's
really it's it can be a really sexy
thing right everybody can get shiny
object syndrome like oh we could double
our Revenue we could add all this extra
capacity but what's your life going to
look like after you close that is is the
business you're looking at is that even
aligned with your values so I would say
before you even think of buying another
business if you've already got a
business you need to make sure that your
financial house for your current
business is in order that you know kind
of what your values are you know what
you stand for and you know what growth
success looks like for you and then at
that point you know you can bring
somebody in with my expertise to help
you evaluate different
opportunities um if you're an
independent investor and you don't
necessarily have a business um but
you're interested in business ownership
again make sure your financial h house
is in order right that you've got enough
Savings in the bank to cover your living
costs and that doing diligence on a
business or buying another business
isn't going to overstretch you you know
if you've got a family with young kids
that's definitely something you're going
to want to
consider that's a great point you know
there's a lot of business owners or not
a lot of business owners just business
owners but there's a lot of uh business
owners and aspiring business owners who
are looking to become entrepreneurs
through acquisition or expand on what
they have and uh you know sometimes they
do it too early you know we're talking
about when the right time is but you
know if you are out there and you're
looking to buy a business and you only
have enough reserves to go through due
diligence with one deal you're probably
not at the right spot to get into
m&a you definitely need to be able to to
go through due diligence to spend that
money and still have the confidence and
wisdom to step away and to get into it
again without breaking the bank I've had
a lot of potential buyers too similarly
who have enough money to effectuate the
deal but are working so much and they
don't have the time and I you know as a
kind of intermediary talking to them you
think are you going to a to do all this
extra work um you know what's the plan
because even if you're delegating all of
it you've got to you know launder it
through yourself and figure out how to
assimilate it to your
systems um to some degree you know it's
not automatic you can't just tuck it in
it's not like you've got to supervise
you've got to meet with clients you've
got to effectuate the transition and
they just don't have the bandwidth
sometimes they realize that and
sometimes they don't and it's just a
complete to launch I've had a couple
deals where I get a call from this um
from either party really and the buyer
just never took over the
business and they just never had the
capacity the sellers continuing to
provide services or do whatever because
they don't you know there usually some
kind of contingent payment they don't
want to lose out on that and they can't
figure out how to just abandon everyone
that they've been working with for years
and years so they're still working
they've already sold the business the
buyer just had hasn't taken it from them
and they can't sell it again so they
call me and say what am I supposed to do
I uh I'm stuck how you know and I just
say like walk away yeah and you know
send the keys back to the buyer in the
mail and just turn your email off
because that's really the only option
well yeah right it's that sunk cost
fallacy they've put so much into the
business it's hard to let it go but
ultimately that would be in their best
interest to take the money that they've
gotten and move move on yeah it's um but
I I can only in those cases I think the
reason that that's happened is because
the buyer completely and utterly bid off
more than they could
chew yeah which and that's that's why
it's so important to have a a strong
Plan before you actually move forward
with buying a
business so with your wealth of
experience Brian and the the financials
and the operational elements of this and
in the due diligence components of of a
deal um what do you recommend how do you
build a plan during the analysis stage
so that you know that you can
effectively take over and succeed at
closing and
Beyond yeah and I think it almost starts
before the analysis stage you know kind
of like we touched on you really need to
be clear on on your values and your
vision not not just business-wise but
personally you know what what do you
want out of life and how can buying this
business how can that serve you long
term because I mean business acquisition
is a great tool for accelerating your
growth but you know like we said you
don't want to get your skis out in front
of you so I think it helps to have kind
of a plan you've got to be clear on your
values and then you've got to be clear
on kind of what does the right deal look
like for you you know like what what
size makes sense um you know financing
wise is what do you think you might be
comfortable with kind of what what
parameters for that qualitatively like
like what types of culture of business
are you looking for you know what types
of people are you looking to bring into
your fold um maybe your business is
currently strong in one particular
service area or geographic region and
does it make sense to expand your
footprint either in your local market or
into other adjacent markets or service
areas so it's kind of mapping out those
factors and then you know having kind of
a consistent process so Financial
diligence is just one leg of the stool
right like obviously you want to make
sure that the business has strong cash
flow and that post acquisition if you're
putting debt on it that it's still going
to be a positively cash flowing asset
for you and there's a lot of things you
know it it pays to have you know a
financial advisor go through and do due
diligence right get a quality of
earnings report because that'll give you
a good sense of the financial health of
the business how strong are the income
streams what do the expense you know
what are the expenses look like for the
business and that also can give you
negotiation leverage right like if the
seller saying they've got an asset
that's got x million in revenue and you
prove that it's actually got x minus y
that's an opportunity to get the asset
at a lower purchase price than what you
thought you might have um but again
Finance is only one leg of the stool
right it's important to have a trusted
legal adviser because there's a lot of
legal issues that might come up it helps
to have you know a a business broker
yeah like could you do the deal on your
own sure but a lot of sellers typically
will have a business broker who's
focused on getting a commission for the
deal and it helps to have maybe a broker
who understands deals of the size you're
considering or in your industry because
that can help make sure that you've got
favorable terms I think abely chiming in
on yeah what Brian says um all those
intermediaries I like your terms the the
legs of the stool um I a lot of those
legs of the stool including your bankers
and Brokers only get paid if the deal
goes through and you already as a
potential acquirer have so much
gravitational pull because of your sunk
costs you're imagining of the future um
you have so much emotional you know time
spent you have a lot of emotional EX in
that basket too so if you're only
talking to bankers and brokers who have
their um you know they've trust me
they've done the numbers and they know
how much money they're going to make if
it goes through and they're motivated by
that too um you know if you can have uh
advisors or mentors or family members
who can be far far enough removed they
don't have any personal interest in
whether it goes through or not and they
can just you know be a sounding board
for you I think it's really really
really value valuable cuz I do think you
get to this point where you've got just
it sucks you in because you you've spent
time um and similarly I mean the role
that you provide Brian I think is very
objective uh when you're going through
that so you've got I mean you get paid
either way too so I think that's a
really valuable somebody who knows under
the hood who sees a lot of deals who
gets paid whether it goes through or not
um and can give you some reasonable
advice and I also wanted to ask so give
us some examples what kills deals when
you see it or what what has um scuttled
something or surprised
everyone sure yeah and I guess I could
give you maybe a deal story to provide
some context on this um so one of the
deals that I I looked at you know years
ago we were advising a small investor
group and it they they had an Loi for
$20 million and they were buying a a
furniture manufacturing business it's
the type of stuff like if you went to
like a restaurant or a hotel hotel with
an outdoor patio um that you would see
their Furniture there and the the owner
had presented kind of an adjusted eBid
do figure which that's a proxy for like
the the operating cash flow for the
business so they' presented a figure of
$2.5
million and in the course of diligence
we determined that that figure should
have actually been $2 million which
would have ultimately I think it was an
8X multiple on the deal so that would
have been like a $4 million haircut to
the price dropping it to 16 million and
and some of the factors that we saw that
resulted in that lower figure well you
know the owner had put forward a lot of
adjustments claiming personal expenses
um which is typically an addback right
if it's stuff that's not needed to run
the business you can you can add that
back um but what we determined was a lot
of these expenses were actually
networking expenses that helped them
generate sales for the business so
a buyer would have had to continue
incurring those costs post close how do
you distinguish that CU I I was
picturing when you were saying that you
know the typical like the standard
addback is oh I my golf membership my
golf club
membership um is and then my car also
and my you know they people come up with
all kinds of things uh slap a sticker
for their business on it and you know
run it through as an expense totally
reasonable until you go to sell and then
you know you've got to try to make an
argument for why that was really income
so you know different people you're
arguing to the IRS it's an expense to
the buyer it's totally just income that
I was redirecting and those people don't
usually talk about that so it's okay to
make different arguments but what kind
of expenses and who makes that
determination that there was a you know
needed marketing expense and that's why
it's so helpful to have you know an
expert who's done this before talk
directly to the seller so you know we
had an interview with the owner of the
business and we started poking into
these expenses like okay you know you
you've got you know 25 Grand here a year
that's for like a country club
membership like is this truly a personal
country club or or how is it being used
and the owner actually admitted to us
that they use that to meet with Pro
prospective clients you know they take
them out for a nice meal and kind of
whine and dine them there and it's like
okay well
it's foreseeable that a potential buyer
would have to continue incurring that
expense post close oh so I guessed it I
made up Country Club and I guessed it
yes yeah I mean that just shows the
experience you have it was at the back
of your mind yeah that's okay so then
you know I guess reasonable Minds might
differ I'm going to be the one to say
the quiet part here because in a world
where everything is being offshored and
sent to teams abroad to offer these high
level services at the lowest price point
possible what Brian just said you know
having an expert who is in the US in the
country that you're in for the
acquisition that you're doing with the
ability to have a meaningful
conversation with the seller and ask
those questions that you don't even know
you need to ask it's critically
important for a QV to be worth what it's
worth um so yeah not something you can
just uh
Outsource well it's like brain surgery
right like do you want to pay the
discount brain surgeon probably not and
if you're spending over a million
dollars on a business right like paying
a a small small percentage of that to
make sure that you know what you're
actually buying it at least in my mind
it gives you that peace of
mind so and that was that was only one
adjustment in the case of this furniture
business we actually discovered that
there had been a recent uptick in sales
but the reason for that was that the
owner was offering favorable pay payment
terms to customers and encouraging them
to purchase more than they might have
otherwise ordered
so and I think it's part of the deal the
the owner wanted to keep their
receivables so they were going to get
the benefit of the payment and the buyer
was going to be footing the bill for a
lot of it oh man and taking probably a
lot more risk so yeah exactly because
that would reduce sales right if they
bought more today than they normally
would they're probably going to buy less
tomorrow
and that's just stuff that you don't
think about or realize until you really
start kicking the
tires well and so the amazing thing
about this concept and I'm so glad that
we're talking about this because it's
one of those Concepts in business
Acquisitions like we're talking about a
$20 million deal so that's on the very
top end of what would be like a small
business like a lower lower mid type
business um in a in a larger like a a
midsize business or even large corporate
setting you know know this just scales
up right the same exact adjustments
could be worth $40
million um but but what's even more
important and more important to to who I
expect our listeners are is that this
can happen on the other side too a a
$50,000 adjustment could mean a100 to
$200,000 difference to the seller which
you know when you're talking about a
very small closely held business that's
big it's a big deal that could be you
know years of your retirement that
you're expecting uh shaved off just
because of you know something that was
an oversight in the business that was
captured under the the QE the quality of
earnings I agree with you I I like to
throw in it's kind of nice being a lower
cost although I know it's very expensive
um provider for small businesses because
there's just a couple things that I do
that I'll go okay that paid for my fees
you know um like all right well let's
talk at the very front end you're going
to take on a commercial lease who gets
the security deposit and I think you can
make a good argument that the buyer can
get assign the security deposit because
they're not going to get a to like you
know repaint a new carpet the whole
thing right um you could I I argue that
same thing both ways depending on who
I'm representing sure but you know the
security deposit laer thing I know right
yeah they like that was usually like 10
$20,000 so we're good you're welcome
um otherwise it was probably not going
to be talked about ever until they were
you know dealing with some kind of hole
in the wall issue later well that's the
thing right to your ear earlier Point
Sarah most people when they're doing a
deal they're thinking about it's like
buying a flight to Hawaii right you're
thinking about the destination not the
hours long flight that you're going to
endure to get there so you really don't
necessarily think about all these
potential pitfalls that could come up
until it's too late and you've got this
asset and then you've got to figure out
how to solve this problem so what
happened with this deal did the the
seller have to take that $4 million
haircut to get to closing so the so so
my client the investor group decided to
cut the price and present our findings
to the seller and the seller said no
they did not want to take a lower price
and it I I found out later that the the
buyer had actually been a little wary
they didn't have full comfort with the
management team and they thought that
industry conditions were starting to
soften a little so it gave them an
excuse as well to back out of the deal
ultimately so if we had to boil this
down to some lessons learned and maybe
even some red flags that that you took
away from this deal to look for in in
other deals um what would you say are
some of the the things that you would
advise someone to keep an eye out for
you know what should they look for in
their quality of earnings report what
should they be aware of in terms of how
they negotiate so that they could make
it to closing whether it's a you know a
a $2 million deal a $20 million deal or
a $200 million deal I guess the first
thing I would say is that not all deals
are worth doing so it's it's really
important right and and that's part of
the problem too especially if you're
going after a business that's being
represented by broker and maybe the
broker is telling you that they've got
other interested parties and oh you'd
better hurry up put your best foot
forward or you might lose the deal right
it it gets into our natural competitive
Spirit every Everybody Wants to win the
deal and it it pays to have a financial
advisor who can help you step back and
say well wait a minute let's make sure
this is in our best interest and that we
kind of know the most that we'd be
willing to pay for the deal and the
terms that make sense so you know it I I
wouldn't recommend trying to do the
financial diligence yourself unless
you've got a lot of experience in that
area and even then it pays to get
another set of eyes cuz you right like
you just don't know it's hard to read a
label when you're stuck inside the jar
um so I guess from a a q of perspective
you know it's definitely making sure
that you understand the revenue streams
right where is the income coming from um
are there unusual kind of one-time
Trends or spikes in Revenue you know cuz
a lot of times when a seller is getting
ready to sell their business they try to
make it look as good as possible Right
like putting a Fresh coat of paint on a
house before you sell it so you want to
make sure there's not those short-term
curb appeal adjustments to the financial
results that ultimately aren't going to
stick around post closing um the other
thing that a lot of people don't factor
into purchase price is working capital
which you know it's it's kind of the
current assets like the receivables the
inventory of the the business less any
current payables you know if you've got
like salaries you've got to pay or other
you know expenses going to your vendors
or suppliers and working capital is
really like it's like if you buy a car
it's making sure there's enough gas in
the tank that on day one as the new
owner you're able to run the business
kind of in line with how it's
historically been run and and that and
Sarah could probably speak to this it's
usually a negotiating point for the the
purchase documents as well there's there
usually a Target that might be set for
it so just making sure that you
understand that um and that's why it's
so important to get a quality of
earnings analysis done because it'll
give you a clear idea of the financial
health of the business it'll help give
you kind of potential red flag so if
there's any points for negotiation
leverage it can help and then the other
big thing is that it gives you
credibility if you're going to seek
third party investors or maybe get an
SBA loan or other Finance ing to help
you make this acquisition it just
signals to them that you're credible and
that you're doing a comprehensive review
of the business before you buy it do you
I mean does the qov assist with this
kind of working capital Peg so people
know what they need and can you know
give them the credibility to negotiate
it typically yes you know that the qvs
that I typically do a look at kind of
the last 12 months or so of working
capital trends for the business we'll
make adjustments for any kind of
irregular or one-time items and then
we'll recommend what a Target should be
for working capital that's great that's
maybe of equal great value for a lot of
the small small buyers who just you know
are kind of it's a shot in the dark and
the seller doesn't know because they
just always keep lots and lots of money
in their checking account yeah critical
part of the deal process too because a
lot of SBA lenders out there want to add
as much working cap Capital as they can
yeah so I I'd love to I mean I want you
to finish your point Brian but I'd love
to also talk about when the qov should
be ordered at what point should it be
done you know after you know you we kind
of go through the steps you know you
find a business you indicate your
interest you talk to the seller you put
in your Loi which we talk about Lois
every time um but when does the QE
happen and how does that how does that
relate back to uh you know what you're
asking the bank
for yeah and really the QV is typically
ordered after you've got exclusive
exclusivity which is kind of the primary
binding function of a letter of intent
the LOI um usually it'll lay out you
know we want 30 to 90 days maybe more
than that exclusivity to perform due
diligence on this business um and that's
typically once you know that the owner
isn't going to use your offer to try to
shop around and get a better deal that's
when as a buyer you would go ahead and
incur the costs of a qov and how long
does a good QE take to get uh just for
timeline purposes so that so that our
listeners know how much to budget
TimeWise sure now and it the timeline
can vary but assuming your diligence
provider gets all the information that
they need in a timely fashion it's
usually a four to five week process is
that pretty hard to get all the
information you need it it can be
yeah that's always a limiting factor
yeah and it goes kind of back to your
earlier point right like you've got
either a busy seller or you've got a a
busy buyer and it's just hard to
allocate time because it's it's a lot of
information that goes into doing proper
diligence and it takes time to gather it
is when you have these smaller deals
they're so much more complex because you
have the owner operators running the
deals and
they're there's no buffer between the
person who's doing all the work the
person who has to keep the wheels from
falling off um the person who's doing
the deal and the emotions of all of that
kind of compounding I actually um in
really small deals don't even push for
exclusivity in the LOI because it's such
a challenge to
enforce um and it's just constantly
broken so it's a a lot of times you know
exclusivity is offered in exchange for
like a deposit of several you know tens
of thousands of dollars and my clients
would rather take the risk of a
different buyer coming through then risk
tens of thousands of dollars so you know
it's but once you're under Loi I think
you can pretty easily ensure uh
exclusivity
by uh taking up all the time of the
owner operator seller in
diligence they don't have time for
another buyer so you're good and that's
also probably a signal too if they're
not responding to your multiple requests
for information maybe they are either
too busy in their business or they're
shopping it around to others the big
takeaway that I'm hearing I mean you get
emotional in these deals and sometimes
you maybe you fall in love with the type
of business the business's culture it's
positioning it's geographic location you
know maybe you're moving from somewhere
very cold to somewhere nice and tropical
and it's it's easy to lose sight of
those obvious indicators that it is okay
not just okay you should walk away you
should walk away from the deal and the
only way that you can really do that
keep an eye on that is with a
professional who is doing a quality of
earnings report during your due
diligence something else that jumped out
that I want to mention real quick is
last week when we were talking to
Shannon hey he mentioned that you know
these smaller deals especially deals
like under 10 million you typically
don't need more than one broker you
don't typically get more than one broker
in the deal and I mentioned some some
ethics elements or some some contention
there about that about that topic but
something that I realized to today with
Brian is that uh you know even if the
broker is unwilling to co-broker a deal
you can always have a fractional CFO in
your corner who uh can help you keep an
eye on the finances keep an eye on those
metrics and if you work with someone
like Brian they understand the mergers
and Acquisitions process as well so a
great person to add on your deal team so
with that Brian uh what would you like
our listeners to know how can they
connect with you and how can they work
with you sure and I again I really
appreciate you guys having me on so as a
special thank you to you and your
listeners I'd love to offer up just a
free financial assessment so if anybody
either has a business and they just want
to make sure that the Financial Health
is okay um or if they're considering
buying a business I'm happy to take an
initial look at the deal there um and I
can offer you know I can point out any
growth opportunities that I see hanging
out any potential red flags that might
be holding them back uh so happy to do
that and I can share a link if your
listeners want to book that call all
right we'll make sure that that's in the
show notes in the description in the
comments wherever you are listening to
this that there will be a link and uh
some information to make that happen uh
thanks so much Brian this is great and
uh yeah I can't wait to have you back to
hear another story and some more lessons
looking forward to it all right so this
has been episode three of the
inquisitive podcast where we break down
deals that don't make it all the way to
closing or are really tough to close so
that you can get those valuable lessons
learn about the red flags and do better
deals yourself thanks for listening and
uh please like And subscribe to support
the podcast so we can keep it going see
you next
time promise my brother soon as he fin
this do it bigbody